debunking common TRT misconceptions.
So I guess we should talk about TRT is
bad for your heart. TRT is bad for your
prostate. You have to donate on TRT. So
all these typical misconceptions, where
do they come from? And why do other
doctors or a lot of other providers keep
on repeating them?
>> I mean, that's the general question for
humanity, right? Why do we repeat things
that we've never looked into as fact?
And my gosh, look at the last few days.
what's going on right now with people
speculating like they know what's going
on with certain events in the world.
They don't. Um, we like to drum up
stories in our head and and when it
comes to hormones, the amount of
storytelling around them and I think a
lot of it, and I'm speculating here,
too. I don't know why the misinformation
is the way it is. I noticed it in med
school because, you know, I grew up
studying steroids, researching things
when I was in high school and later into
college. Like, I really enjoyed the
topic. And even then, you you get a feel
for how people think about hormones and
even just general testosterone
replacement. It gets the stigma. And I
think it probably is because of the um
performance-enhancing world, maybe the
abuse side. Um and they equate the two
things, which is a total nonsequiter. It
doesn't follow that because you can
abuse something that using it is wrong
or dangerous. Uh you can abuse water,
whatever, you know? I mean, it's just
insane. But um that that just sticks and
you you hear it from I mean I heard it
in med school over and over and over
again even from just med students who
didn't know anything about anything yet
and oh yeah those hormones they're hor I
can't believe somebody put something on
hormones and so I don't know the motives
behind it. I don't understand the
mindset. It just is out there and it's I
think it's slowly getting better. The I
I'm seeing a shift uh in some of the
physician groups I'm in on Facebook. A
lot of urologists especially are wanting
to get into the hormone space,
but they still are believing a lot of
things that are wrong, but at least
they're more open to even doing it. I
mean, 20 years ago, there's no, you
don't need that. You know, it's just
crazy. Um, so I don't know the wise, but
people repeat dogmas uh as truth without
looking into it. They've done this for
several things you mentioned, right?
They've done it for uh things about
donating blood, the high hematocrit, you
know, on testosterone replacement,
prostate cancer stuff, estradile. Those
would be the three big I would say
misconceptions.
Um and then the heart disease, stroke
risk, that's thankfully been looked at
in meta analyses at this point. Like you
can pretty much mark that off the list.
There's and I don't like statistical
studies because you you can't compare
something inside an individual to
themselves. you're comparing different
people in different groups and then
you're looking for differences. It's
like, yeah, but you don't know what
would have happened in that one
individual over time, you know,
whatever. But it's the best we have and
if you don't see an increase in
association, maybe you can at least mark
it off as a causation and that's kind of
the best I see for those kind of
studies. So I think when you see that in
the uh studies done on on cardiovascular
risk, cardiovascular disease, MI,
strokes, DVTs, there's just no no
increased association with that even and
and I don't even see that they're
controlling hematocrit in a lot in a lot
of those studies at all. That's what I
always tell people. But um there's no
evidence that increased hematocrit as on
its own like that lab value causes
anything bad like causation wise. People
speculate all day long about viscosity.
They call it thick blood. If you go and
look at viscosity research, most of it's
all done outside of the body. You can't
actually check the viscosity inside the
body. And if you look at some studies
done, the viscosities are actually worse
in those with lower hemoglobin hematic
or at least in ape ape studies and
things like that. They don't really
study this in humans. There's not a good
incentive to study it. Um, but from what
I tell people is here's here's my
philosophy on it. And if other people
disagree, I'm fine with that. We all
have our boundaries. My philosophy for
all these things is if I don't have
actual evidence to to recommend an
intervention, I cannot in good
conscience recommend it. What I can tell
you is those interventions come with
costs themselves. So in my mindset of as
a physician do no harm. How can I
recommend somebody do a procedure or
take a drug without any evidence behind
it when I know those things doing those
things can actually cause harm. So
that's my stance on that. Whether it
comes to frequent phbotoies which can
cause harm. You're literally mimicking a
hemorrhage acutely and that causes a
cascade of things in the body and also
causes overcompensation. We see it all
the time in the Facebook group, right? I
keep donating and my hematocrit ends up
higher than it was. It's like yeah,
that's uh that's pretty normal. Human
physiology, the body the body is
designed very well and so it will
respond accordingly. And so you would
have to bleed out pretty frequently to
keep that number low. Well, then what
are you doing? Why are you doing that?
You know, all to chase a number that
nobody can prove is a problem. Um, and
so that's that's my first thing on on
the myths about hematic or hemoglobin.
U, prostate cancer thankfully has been
looked at for at least 20 years now, and
they've kind of debunked all that myth
that testosterone either causes it or
even fuels it. I hope that spills over
into the female world soon because the
same dogma is repeated about estradiol
when there's just no good evidence for
that. Now, is there evidence that some
hormones can cause harm? Yeah, but not
all hormones are the same. People like
to make these um hasty generalizations,
right? And they they put everything into
one category. It's just like people do
with carbohydrates, you know, in the oh,
oh, because this one these few over here
maybe may be bad, therefore all carbs
are bad. It's like, no, everything
stands or falls on its own. Um, so it's
going to be the same thing with with
these hormones and and cancer risks and
things like that. But um you know I
always tell people of course if if you
have a hormone sensitive tissue that
becomes cancerous or a part of it does
it's still going to be hormone
sensitive. The hormones aren't causing
that. And of course if you withdraw the
hormones you might see the tissue shrink
away and shrivel. People equate
shriveling a tumor with a good outcome
when it's like you don't know that doing
that is actually doing anything for why
that cancer is there in the first place.
You're just chasing an effect, right?
You can do it with chemo. I could I
could cut off a blood supply to a tumor
and shrink it. That has nothing to do
with the total health of the person.
>> Um, so people don't I think hard enough
on these topics and they're chasing
effects instead of chasing root causes.
Um, but again, there's no evidence that
testosterone causes or fuels prostate
cancer. I think I've talked about this
before. I had guys as a practicing
urologist who had prostate cancer like
low grad. They were doing surveillance
and they wanted to be on TRT. And based
on the many studies done on that with
Dr. from Morgan Tyler's group. I was
comfortable doing that. And guess what?
None of them that I ever saw had sudden
rapid progression of their cancer. In
fact, a lot of the PSA numbers got
better. Not that PSA is a great test. It
can change all the time, but in general,
people with prostate cancer, it will
slowly, you know, rise over time. And I
would see their PSA numbers improve. Um,
and is that because their health got
better? I I don't know. That's all
speculative. What what I saw was no no
increased risk. And they felt better.
they felt like humans again. So these
people that are wanting to castrate them
or keep them castrated all to chase a
PSA marker on its own, they're not
taking into account the whole person and
what their goals are in life and their
desires, you know. Um and then as far as
uh the estradile, I mean that's the one
we've hammered before. That's a big myth
misconception. Uh I'm going to be
talking about that this uh coming
November at the Silverback Summit. I'm
going to give a little talk on
estradile. Again, just kind of a
refresher. I think it's good to rehash
that topic over and over again and yeah,
but you know what people don't
understand is that the
>> they chase again a lab number that can't
really be validated to mean anything at
all. A serum estradile value in a male
is pretty much useless. Um because the
at least according to the research and
how it's done, the aromatization process
takes place once testosterone enters the
tissue itself. uh and then it converts
and that's going to happen in varying
amounts depending on the tissues needs
and all these other things. So it's
essentially an intricate process which
we talked about and measuring a serum
level you don't know what it means and
so and it will always be above normal
pretty much in anyone taking
testosterone because those normal values
baselines are not obtained from people
taking these compounds. So you would
have to have a whole different set of
normals for people on the hormones to
even get a statistical distribution. But
even then, statistics don't tell you
anything about where one ought to be as
an individual. So that's the
philosophical issue there. So yeah, the
those would be the big misconceptions.
Uh or you know the little ones like, oh,
it's going to give you roid rage, you're
going to rage, you're going to be an
angry person.
>> I don't see it. Honestly, I've take I
take testosterone. I've taken steroids.
Like I didn't rage with any of them. But
in general, my guys on get on
testosterone feel completely better.
Their their moods improve. Uh, and I
know you've seen it, too. We see it all
the time, just how much better people
feel in general, a little more just
resilient to stressors. Now, I do think
some people when they get on
testosterone, if they've been a bump on
a log for a while, they may become more
assertive as they're feeling better. And
that can come across, let's say, to a
spouse, a wife that was used to running
the show. um that can come across as
angry, right? Well, okay, if you want to
call it that, but he may just finally be
feeling good enough to like assert
himself. And I I have seen that happen.
But in general, I just see people's
moods improve. I don't see the rage and
and all this stuff. So,
>> maybe one more. You're going to lose
your hair because you're on TRT.
>> Yeah. Again, there's plenty of guys,
this is my whole thing. I'm like,
not the majority of men in general will
lose their hair over time, TRT or not.
That's just the way it is.
>> So, you can't prove that TRT ever caused
it in the first place. A lot of people
will see shedding, but shedding comes
cycllically, too. Like, there's
different growth phases and things like
that. Stress. I mean, we're all under so
much stress in America especially, but
westernized countries, you can lose your
hair for lots of reasons, poor food,
poor diet, poor sleep. U But it's not a
given that taking testosterone will
cause you is gonna you're going to lose
your hair. But I do want men to
understand that it's going to be a fact
of life that most of us will have hair
recession at least at some point or in
certain places. I mean, I'm getting it
here, right? Uh it's just part of it.
And I I don't think twice about it. The
guys who I understand the the desire not
to lose the hair. Like I I don't want
to, but at what cost are you going to
try to prevent that? And that's where I
try to counsel people that if you really
want to preserve it, I mean, you're
going to probably have to do something
radical, whether it be take some kind of
pill that you hope works that's going to
wreck your health, like a finasteride or
minoxidil or something like that, or you
go and get surgery done, you know, the
little transplant. And that's probably
at the end of the day, if you really
want to maintain your hair or have more,
that's probably a smarter way to do it,
honestly, than taking drugs. Um because
the drugs don't do do what people hope
they do per se and they do cause harm.
And so that to me again do no harm. It's
like I can't if guys want to do it
they'll tell me you know patients will
ask me about it and I'll counsel them. I
wouldn't recommend it and I won't
prescribe that. If they want to do it on
their own go for it. Um I do recommend
if you're going to do something do and
not do surgery do a topical over a
systemic. You're still going to absorb
some of it but you may have a less less
systemic effects doing topical than a
pill.
Hey,
hey,
hey.